Repentance towards father
I have been listening
to your teachings regularly
and I felt my priority was
to repent towards my father
So I started my prayer of
repentance on my own.
But it's not going as well as I thought.
My heart is not in it so I wanted
to ask for a prayer script.
To tell you a little bit about my father,
he imposed a lot of restrictions
on me ever since I was young.
Rather than being kind or warm, he used to
be harsh and angry with me a lot.
I thought he wasn't someone
I could lean on or need.
Rather, I was intimidated
and I wanted to avoid him.
Naturally, I resented him a lot.
When I was young, I was scared of him.
Since I could not take it out on him,
I directed my anger towards my mother.
Then, around the time of my graduation from
college, he passed away from an illness.
Now I live with my mother,
just the two of us.
My mother is old.
She is very ill.
She always expresses her anguish to me
and says 'What happened to me?'
Knowing that she has had a very hard life,
I try to be kind and
accommodating to her always.
I try my best, but her sighs
seem to carry over to me
and make me feel very stifled.
There is nothing I can do for her,
but she always complains to me.
(Questioner) And since I meet
a lot of people in my social life,
(Questioner) I tend to get discouraged
the way I was with my father.
If someone talks to me in a forceful way,
even though I want to
resolve things smoothly,
when things don't work out,
I tend to avoid and feel intimidated.
So I get scared from the very beginning
and instead of voicing my opinion,
I would hide it.
Then I explode in anger and
am unable to maintain the conversation.
As I studied Buddhism, I started
thinking that my father was frustrated,
because his life did not
turn out the way he wanted.
So instead of blaming my father for
everything, I wanted to understand him.
That's why I started
my prayer of repentance.
But I could not concentrate.
I start with thoughts of him but soon,
I'd get distracted and
think about other things.
So, I wanted to ask you how I should pray
for repentance towards my father,
and how I should pray in general.
I really wanted to ask you this.
(Sunim laughter)
Are you married?
(Questioner) No, I am not.
So you live with your mother.
Your mother had a hard life, right?
Even though you understand
she had a hard life,
when she starts sighing and complaining
to you, you feel stifled or not?
(Questioner)
Stifled. She sighs every night.
Since you feel so stifled,
when you are talking with your mother,
you get upset or angry even
without you realizing it, right?
Very often.
(Sunim) So, if it is this stifling for
you who knows well how hard she suffered,
when you hear her sighing and
repeating her stories over and over again,
even you want to say, enough.
Even as her daughter,
you want to say, "enough!'
How do you think your father
felt with a wife like that?
Though he knew that his wife worked hard
and had a hard life,
(Sunim) if you were the husband
and had this sort of wife,
wouldn't you feel so suffocating?
(Questioner) Yes, very much.
Even as a daughter you get
frustrated and angry,
a husband, who thought of himself
above her, would get angry, right?
When she kept repeating
the same stories over and over,
your father would get frustrated.
In addition to his personality,
his troubled relationship with
your mother made him this way.
He would feel uptight with
a wife who nagged him.
So, he ended up lashing out
on the children at home.
So, when you pray, say, " I didn't know
any better because I was young."
"You must have suffered a lot with a wife
with whom you couldn't communicate."
"I understand now your anger towards me."
Prayers should make sense logically.
Just saying, I was wrong,
or sorry doesn't make sense.
Without knowing what you have done wrong,
repentance prayer is meaningless.
That is why you get distracted.
So, imagine how it was for him in the light
of your own experience with your mom.
He must have had a hard time with her.
Up to now, you only recognized
your mom's hardship.
You can see that it must be hard
to live without a husband.
Now that you want to repent to your father,
you need to understand him.
You ought to repent with this mindset.
First, understand
how your father must have felt
living with a woman like your mother.
How difficult and how suffocating,
it must have been.
That is why he was often angry at me.
Second, since I was so young, I was not
able to understand his feeling at all.
Instead, I was scared of him
and resented him only.
"I am sorry,
I was too young to understand."
"Now that I am older, I am able to
understand you a little better."
"I repent."
You have to pray like this so that your
heartache would be dissolved.
And now when you meet a man who
is older or who is like your father,
with prayers like this, you will be
able to understand him as well.
With this understanding of your father
and praying in this manner,
the fear and intimidation you felt
will dissipate.
"He, too, must have his reasons."
"He must have felt frustrated also."
"Since I must be like my mother, he could
have been frustrated by my behaviors."
So, if you begin to understand him
this way, your fear will disappear.
So, offer the prayer of repentance
towards your father in this manner.